Finding aid for Jay G. Hayden scrapbooks, 1916-1965
Bentley Historical Library
Jay G. Hayden scrapbooks
1916-1965
Bentley Historical Library
Hayden, Jay G., 1884-1971
851754 Aa 2
8 linear feet (46 volumes.)
Newspaper articles and columns by Detroit News Washington correspondent, include extensive comment on national politics and foreign relations, particularly as they relate to Michigan
The collection was donated by Jay G. Hayden (Donor no. 4629 ).
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Jay G. Hayden retired on March 1, 1965, after 65 years in the newspaper business. The acknowledged dean of Washington correspondents, he wrote from the capitol for the Detroit News for more than 49 years.
He was born December 8, 1884, in Cassopolis, Michigan, and grew up on his father's farm, and was willing to work at anything to get away from the cows. He worked for a series of small newspaper presses throughout high school and college, including the Vigilant, the Escanaba Daily Mirror, and the University of Michigan print shop.
In 1915 he went to Washington, D.C., and by 1918 he was Washington Bureau chief. He was one of two US news correspondents accredited to sit in on the signing of the Treaty of Versailles, and he set up a London Bureau for the Detroit News in the same year. His travels also included the Philippines, China, and Japan.
He died on October 24, 1971, and is buried in Cassopolis, Michigan.
Scrapbooks, 1916-1965, of Jay G. Hayden, Washington correspondent for the Detroit News, contain extensive comment on national politics and foreign relations, particularly as they relate to Michigan. Personal subjects include: Sherman Adams, Smith W. Brookhart, Prentiss M. Brown, William Jennings Bryan, James F. Byrnes, Benjamin N. Cardozo, James Couzens, George Creel, Charles DeGualle, Edwin Denby, Lewis Douglas, John Foster Dulles, Dwight D. Eisenhower, James A. Farley, Henry Ford, Felix Frankfurter, John Glenn, James Hoffa, Herbert Hoover, Lyndon B. Johnson, John F. Kennedy, Nikita Khrushchev, Robert M. LaFollette, Douglas McArthur, Joe McCarthy, Andrew Mellon, James Meredith, Billy Mitchell, Frank Murphy, Truman H. Newberry, Richard M. Nixon, Sam Rayburn, Owen J. Roberts, Nelson A. Rockefeller, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Frank L. Smith, Joseph Stalin, Harlan F. Stone, Harry S. Truman, Arthur H. Vandenberg, William S. Vare, Henry A. Wallace and Leonard Wood.
African Americans -- Michigan.; Agriculture.; Nuclear energy.; Depressions -- 1929 -- United States.; Detroit (Mich.); Elections -- Michigan -- 1922.; Elections -- New York (State) -- 1958.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; Labor movement -- United States.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1917-1921.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1922-1928.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1929-1938.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1939-1945.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1946-1960.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1961-1970.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; American newspapers.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1920.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1924.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1928.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1932.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1936.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1940.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1944.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1948.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1952.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1960.; Presidents -- United States -- Election -- 1964.; Prohibition -- United States.; Soviet Union.; Street-railroads -- United States.; Tariff -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations.; United States -- Politics and government -- 20th century.; World War, 1914-1918.; World War, 1939-1945.; Scrapbooks.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1837-1950.; Michigan -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Detroit news.; Adams, Sherman, 1899-1986.; Brookhart, Smith Wildman, 1869-1944.; Brown, Prentiss M. (Prentiss Marsh), 1889-1973.; Bryan, William Jennings, 1860-1925.; Byrnes, James F. (James Francis), 1882-1972.; Cardozo, Benjamin N. (Benjamin Nathan), 1870-1938.; Couzens, James, 1872-1936.; Creel, George, 1876-1953.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Denby, Edwin, 1870-1929.; Douglas, Lewis W. (Lewis Williams), 1894-1974.; Dulles, John Foster, 1888-1959.; Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Dwight David), 1890-1969.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Ford, Henry, 1863-1947.; Frankfurter, Felix, 1882-1965.; Gaulle, Charles de, 1890-1970.; Glenn, John, 1921-; Hayden, Jay G., 1884-1971.; Hoffa, James R. (James Riddle), 1913-; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973.; Kennedy, John F. (John Fitzgerald), 1917-1963.; Khrushchev, Nikita Sergeevich, 1894-1971.; Ku Klux Klan (1915-); La Follette, Robert M. (Robert Marion), 1855-1925.; League of Nations.; MacArthur, Douglas, 1880-1964.; McCarthy, Joseph, 1908-1957.; Mellon, Andrew W. (Andrew William), 1855-1939.; Meredith, James, 1933-; Mitchell, William, 1879-1936.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.; States' Rights Democratic Party.; Newberry, Truman Handy, 1864-1945.; Nixon, Richard M. (Richard Milhous), 1913-1994.; Progressive Party (U.S.: 1948); Rayburn, Sam, 1882-1961.; Republican Party (Mich.); Roberts, Owen J. (Owen Josephus), 1875-1955.; Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich), 1908-1979.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Smith, Frank Leslie, 1867-1950.; Stalin, Joseph, 1879-1953.; Stone, Harlan Fiske, 1872-1946.; Truman, Harry S., 1884-1972.; Union Party (1936-1938); United Nations.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1922.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1934.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1942.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1946.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1954.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1956.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1958.; United States. Congress -- Elections, 1962.; United States. Supreme Court.; Vandenberg, Arthur H. (Arthur Hendrick), 1884-1951.; Vare, Wm. S. (William Scott), 1867-1934.; Wallace, Henry Agard, 1888-1965.; Wood, Leonard, 1860-1927.
- Scrapbooks
  - Volume 1, November 25, 1916-December 7, 1917 (Box 1)
    (concerning prohibition, military preparedness, Armed-Ship Bill, War Industries Board, the draft, women suffrage and the Robert M. LaFollette controversy)
  - Volume 2, December 8, 1917-August 31, 1918 (Box 1)
    (concerning prohibition, the Creel Committee, censorship. World War I. and maritime controls)
  - Volume 3, September 2, 1918-October 4, 1919 (Box 1)
    (concerning the Truman H. Newberry controversy, troop involvement in Russia, negotiations on the League of Nations and the Treaty of Versailles)
  - Volume 4, October 19, 1919-August 30, 1920 (Box 1)
    (concerning the Truman H. Newberry controversy, the Red Scare, Treaty of Versailles, Senatorial investigation of General Leonard Wood's career, municipal ownership of the Detroit Street Railways and nominating presidential candidates)
  - Volume 5, September 1, 1920-April 30, 1922 (Box 1)
    (concerning the Truman H. Newberry controversy, presidential campaign, railroad, freight and emergency tariff)
  - Volume 6, December 10, 1920-October 27, 1922 (Box 1)
    (concerning the Truman H Newberry controversy, St Lawrence Seaway and Henry Ford's attempt to purchase Muscle Shoals)
  - Volume 7, May 2, 1921-January 14, 1922 (Box 2)
    (concerning the Truman H. Newberry controversy, Washington Conference and formation of the Farm Bloc)
  - Volume 8, January 16, 1922-February 28, 1923 (Box 2)
    (concerning veterans, St. Lawrence Seaway, Teapot Dome scandal, Fordney-McCumber Tariff, the Farm Bloc, Truman H. Newberry controversy, Henry Ford's attempt to purchase Muscle Shoals, campaign of Woodbridge N. Ferris and appointment of James Couzens to the United States Senate)
  - Volume 9, March 2, 1923-March 7, 1924 (Box 2)
    (concerning defeat of United States entry into the World Court, controversy between James Couzens and Andrew W. Mellon, the presidency and the resignation of Edwin Denby as Secretary of the Navy)
  - Volume 10, March 18, 1924-March 20, 1925 (Box 2)
    (concerning prohibition, Couzens-Mellon controversy, Teapot Dome scandal, Muscle Shoals issue, presidential conventions and campaigns, appointment of Supreme Court justices, Billy Mitchell controversy and the Ku Klux Klan)
  - Volume 11, March 20, 1925-August 14, 1926 (Box 2)
    (concerning Couzens-Mellon controversy, World Court, unseating of Senator Smith W. Brookhart, deaths of Robert M. LaFollette and William Jennings Bryan and report on Japan)
  - Volume 12, August 14, 1926-December 3, 1927 (Box 3)
    (concerning prohibition, report on Far East, veto of McNary-Haugen farm subsidy bill, attempts to unseat senators Frank L. Smith and. William S. Vare, and the Hoover presidential campaign)
  - Volume 13, December 5, 1927-February 8, 1929 (Box 3)
    (concerning James Couzens, veto of second. McNary-Haugen farm subsidy bill, election of Herbert Hoover, speculation on Hoover Cabinet and Senatorial investigation of the "Power Trust)
  - Volume 14, February 9, 1929-May 5, 1930 (Box 3)
    (concerning the Hoover Cabinet, the Hawley-Snoot tariff, Wickersham Report or Prohibition and the London Naval conference)
  - Volume 15, May 7, 1930-October 3, 1931 (Box 3)
    (concerning appointment of Owen J. Roberts as Supreme Court Justice, the Hawley-Smoot Tariff and congressional elections)
  - Volume 16, October 5, 1931-November 5, 1932 (Box 3)
    (concerning establishment of the Reconstruction Finance Corporation, LaFollette-Costigan Unemployment Relief Bill, Seabury Investigation arid presidential nominations and campaigns)
  - Volume 17, November 9, 1932-December 22, 1933 (Box 4)
    (concerning Franklin D. Roosevelt's election and cabinet, bank failures, New Deal legislation, London Economic Conference and Pecora Investigation)
  - Volume 18, December 25, 1933-September 1, 1934 (Box 4)
    (concerning Pecora Investigation, defeat of St. Lawrence Waterway Treaty, resignation of Levis Douglas as Director of the Budget and congressional campaigns)
  - Volume 19, September 1, 1934-June 25, 1935 (Box 4)
    (concerning the Congressional elections, the National Recovery Administration, attempt to depose James Farley as Postmaster General)
  - Volume 20, June 26, 1935-June 23, 1936 (Box 4)
    (concerning Public Utilities Holding Company Act the Agricultural Adjustment Act (declared unconstitutional), Guffey-Coal Control Act (declared unconstitutional), American League's opposition to F.D. Roosevelt and the Republican Convention)
  - Volume 21, June 24, 1936-June 17, 1937 (Box 4)
    (concerning, the Democratic Convention, formation of the Union Party, F.D. Roosevelt's reelection, Flint Sit-down Strike, the "Court-Packing" Bill, World Court controversy, enacting neutrality laws and National Labor Relations Act declared constitutional)
  - Volume 22, June 18, 1937-June 3, 1938 (Box 4)
    (concerning the "Court-Packing" Bill, Fair Labor Standards Act and Roosevelt's Reorganization Bill)
  - Volume 23, June 4, 1939-August 5, 1939 (Box 5)
    (concerning Fair Labor Standards Act, death of Justice Benjamin N. Cordozo and appointment of Felix Frankfurter to the Supreme Court, Munich Pact, Congressional elections, Frank Murphy appointed Attorney-General and formation of an anti-New Deal coalition in Congress)
  - Volume 24, August 1939-November 2, 1940 (Box 5)
    (concerning World War II, and the presidential campaign and election)
  - Volume 25, November 23, 1940-February 26, 1942 (Box 5)
    (concerning Lend Lease legislation, appointment of Harlan F Stone as Chief Justice of the Supreme Court and attack on Pearl Harbor)
  - Volume 26, February 27, 1942-July 1, 1943 (Box 5)
    (concerning Congressional elections, allied invasion of North Africa and appointment of Prentiss M. Brown as head of Office of Price-Administrations)
  - Volume 27, July 2, 1943-October 11, 1944 (Box 5)
    (concerning Allied invasion of Italy, relations with Joseph Stalin, labor strikes and presidential conventions)
  - Volume 28, October 12, 1944-January 25, 1946 (Box 6)
    (concerning presidential election, Yalta Conference, Harry S. Truman, United Nations Conference, labor unions, James F. Byrnes appointment as Secretary of State, end of World War II and Pearl Harbor investigation)
  - Volume 29, January 26, 1946-May 15, 1947 (Box 6)
    (concerning Arthur Vandenberg's internationalist speech in the Senate, Congressional elections and the Truman Doctrine)
  - Volume 30., May 16, 1947-April 19, 1948 (Box 6)
    (concerning Marshall Plan, formation of Henry Wallace's third party and the Wedemeyer Report on the failure of China Policy)
  - Volume 31, April 20, 1948-April 20, 1949 (Box 6)
    (concerning political conventions and election, revolt of the Dixiecrats, Berlin Airlift, appointment of Dean Acheson as Secretary of State and NATO)
  - Volume 32, April 21, 1949-May 6, 1950 (Box 6)
    (concerning death of Justice Frank Murphy, Communist revolution in China, Russia, and the atomic bomb and McCarthyism)
  - Volume 33, May 8, 1950-May 12, 1951 (Box 7)
    (concerning outbreak of Korean War, firing of General McArthur and death of Arthur Vandenberg)
  - Volume 34, May 14, 1951-May 13, 1952 (Box 7)
    (concerning Dwight D Eisenhower and McCarthyism)
  - Volume 35, May 14, 1952-June 29, 1953 (Box 7)
    (concerning political conventions and election)
  - Volume 36, June 30, 1953-October 21, 1954 (Box 7)
    (consists mostly of editorials concerning Far Eastern affairs)
  - Volume 37, April 3, 1954-June 21, 1955 (Box 7)
    (concerning the St. Lawrence Seaway and Communist activities in Central America)
  - Volume 38, October 25, 1954-February 17, 1956 (Box 7)
    (concerning Congressional elections and Far Eastern policy)
  - Volume 39, February 18, 1956-March 27, 1957 (Box 7)
    (concerning school desegregation in the South, NATO, presidential conventions and campaigns, Middle Eastern affairs resulting from the Suez Crisis, Hungarian Revolution and the Eisenhower Doctrine)
  - Volume 40, March 28, 1957-May, 1958 (Box 8)
    (concerning McClellen Committee on labor racketeering, school desegregation, Civil Rights legislation, racial problems in Little Rock, the Eisenhower scandals and foreign affairs)
  - Volume 41, May 29, 1958-September 3, 1959 (Box 8)
    (concerning school desegregation, Middle East, resignation of Sherman Adams, Red China's attack on Quemoy and Matsu islands, Congressional elections, Charles DeGualle, election of Nelson Rockefeller as governor of New York, resignation of John Poster Dulles, McClellan Committee investigation of Jimmy Hoffa and economic recession)
  - Volume 42, June 14, 1957-January 20, 1958 (Box 8)
    (concerning McClellan of Jimmy Hoffa, school integration in Little Rock and attempt to launch the Vanguard rocket)
  - Volume 43, September 4, 1959-November 3, 1960 (Box 8)
    (concerning Nikita Khrushchev's visit to the United States, Landrum-Griffin Bill, relations with Cuba, presidential campaign and the U-2 incident)
  - Volume 44, November 4, 1960-January 16, 1962 (Box 8)
    (concerning election of John F. Kennedy, the Congo crisis, the Bay of Pigs fiasco, death of Sam Rayburn and Latin American affairs)
  - Volume 45, January 17, 1962-October 1, 1963 (Box 8)
    (concerning space flight of John Glenn, obstruction of President Kennedy's programs, Congressional elections, defeat of Richard Nixon in race for California governorship, James Meredith at the University of Mississippi, Russia-China conflict and Nuclear Test Ban Treaty)
  - Volume 46, October 3, 1963-March 1, 1965 (Box 8)
    (concerning assassination of President John F. Kennedy and Lyndon Johnson becomes president, presidential conventions and election, Viet Nam War and retirement of Jay G. Hayden)